# 大家好 兄弟很久都沒有跟我聊過天啦
Hi everyone! My buddy hasn't talked with me for a long time.
# 估計我猜他家的那個西瓜肯定熟啦
I think, I bet his watermelons must be ripe now.
# 帶了兩個籮筐
So I come with two baskets,
# 去他家的那個瓜地裡面挑
to go to his farm and take some,
# 挑點西瓜回來
take some watermelons back home.
# 刀又沒帶
My knife is not here.
# 誒 剛好這裡有把刀
Eh? It just so happens that here's a knife.
# 這把刀 可以
This knife, is good enough.
# 帶一個杆子過來
And I have a pole with me.
# 帶上
Take the,
# 刀去備用一下
the knife with me, just in case
# 剛好把這個小 小女兒抬過去
Nice! It can also carry my little, little daughter.
# 抬過去吃 吃飽再回來啊
Let me take her there to eat, and come back when she has eaten enough.
# 哇 還有一個瀑布 漂不漂亮
Wa! Here's a waterfall too. Is it pretty?
# 瀑布靚不靚
Is the waterfall beautiful?
# 你看 兄弟家的香瓜
Look! My buddy's oriental melons,
# 壞了都不叫我們
he didn't call us and simply let them go rotten.
# 有幾個都壞掉啦
A couple of them are already rotten.
# 這有一個
Here's still one.
# 誒呀 這個也壞啦 這個
Eya! This is also rotten, this one,
# 那麼大都壞啦
though it's so large.
# 這也壞掉啦
This is also rotten.
# 你看 這裡一個
Look! Here's one.
# 它好像還不是很熟
But it doesn't seem completely ripe.
# 你看 這個 這有點裂開啦
Look! This one, this one is a bit cracked open.
# 嗯 剛剛好
Um! Perfect!
# 嗯 可以喲
Um! Not bad
# 這有點壞啦
It's a bit rotten.
# 我們就不要
We're not taking it.
# 我們吃那好的
Let's eat only the good part.
# 我們這種香瓜是有那個機肥種出來的哦
Our oriental melons here are grown with organic fertiliser, you know.
# 就是種下去不怎麼管
It means, they don't need much care.
# 它就長到那麼靚的
They can always grow well and are always so beautiful,
# 而且很膽
and are really crunchy too.
# 去摘點西瓜啦
Let's pick some watermelons.
# 放在這裡
I leave them here,
# 放這旁邊
put them aside.
# 給你吃
It's for you.
# 你看
Look!
# 西瓜
Watermelons
# 那麼小
They're so small.
# 我以為很大呢
I thought they were big.
# 刀都不用啦
I don't even need the knife.
# 你看 這種西瓜
Look! This kind of watermelons,
# 這種西瓜就已經熟透了的
a watermelon like this one means it is completely ripe.
# 啊 這個西瓜那麼小 我以為很大呢
Oh! This watermelon is so small. I though it were big.
# 跟我的頭一樣大
It's about the size my of head.
# 你看 這個也摘的 這個
Look! This can also be picked, this one.
# 哎呀 這種小西瓜 剛剛好
Aya! This kind of small watermelons, is perfect,
# 一個人吃一個
single person portion.
# 這個也行
This one is also good.
# 你看 這種西瓜 哎呀
Look! This kind of watermelons... aya!
# 七八斤
three to four kilograms
# 剛好夠我一個人吃
It's just enough for me alone.
# 這個大
This one is huge.
# 哎喲 這一個大的
Ayo! This one is big!
# 大不大
Is it big?
# 你抱不動
You can't hold it.
# 你又跑到這裡來 割腳腳的
Why are you coming here? It cuts your footie.
# 快點
C'mon!
# 很靚的 這兩個小的
These two small ones are, really beautiful!
# 媽媽我肚痛
Mama! My tummy hurts!
# 你看 這兩個大的
Look! These two are big.
# 這個
This is,
# 大西瓜
a giant watermelon.
# 不信 挑不起來
I can take it. Nothing is possible.
# 可以 可以 可以
Yea, yea, yea!
# 剛剛好
It's just right!
# 你看 兄弟家還有這個眉豆哦 (註︰他現在說眉豆，之後說扁豆，我都不知是甚麼豆，總之豆算了)
Look! My buddy has this kind of beans as well.
# 這個眉豆很好吃的
These beans are really tasty.
# 扁眉豆
The flat beans
# 不是吧 就一個
You kidding? Just one?
# 這一個 這沒用的 這個
This one, this is useless, this one.
# 壞的
It's rotten.
# 哎呀 這裡還有兩個
Aya! Here are two more.
# 你看 這個眉豆
Look! These beans...
# 誒 這裡還有一個
Eh? Here's one more.
# 就一餐啊 剛剛好
It's a perfect portion, for one meal,
# 剛好煮一餐
one single meal.
# 哎喲
Ayo!
# 剛好夠一餐
It's one meal portion,
# 一個小家庭
No too much, not too little
# 剛好夠吃
for a small family
# 還有沒有
Any more?
# 這天氣太熱啦
It's too hot now.
# 汗都出來啦
I'm even sweating.
# 你看 這個扁豆
Look! These beans...
# 剛好去買點 買點豬肉
We can just buy some, buy some pork.
# 豬肉炒一下這篇豆很好吃的哦
It's really tasty when these beans are fried with pork.
# 等一下 我要帶回去
I'll bring them back in a while.
# 你看 這還有兩個絲瓜哦
Look! Here are two sponge gourds too.
# 刀都沒帶
But my knife is not with me.
# 把它擰斷
I just twist them off.
# 這裡有一個
Here's one.
# 這種絲瓜很靚的
These sponge gourds are really beautiful.
# 打湯很好 很好吃的哦 這裡有一個
You know, making a soup with them is really tasty. Here's one.
# 靚吧
Beautiful, isn't it?
# 你看 摘了那麼一點點
Look! I've picked just a tiny little bit here.
# 兄弟 這個玉米是不是你家的
Hey man! Are these corns yours?
# 是啊
Yup!
# 熟了哦
They're ripe now.
# 沒熟
No, they aren't!
# 熟啦 你看 那個鬚都老啦
Yes, they are! Look! The silk is already getting old!
# 沒熟都沒熟
Well, let it be no then.
# 看一下還有沒有其它的
Let me see if there is anything else.
# 沒有熟啊 下次來
They're not ripe. Come again next time.
# 辣椒 辣椒
Chilli, chilli
# 等下次熟的時候我再 我再叫你過來摘
I'll call you, call you to come again when they're ripe.
# 你看 那些瓜子那些
Look! The gourds, there,
# 那麼多瓜子都老啦
there are so many of them and they're already old.
# 這生薑 生薑很靚的哦 這生薑 你看
The ginger, ginger is really beautiful. The ginger, look!
# 還沒長大 可以挖 可以挖啦 差不多 (註︰原字幕沒有寫下「還沒長大」，但一拼翻譯會較有趣)
They haven't grown up yet.
We can dig them up, dig them up. They're ready now.
# 還沒長大 這個
They have not yet grown up, the ginger.
# 沒長大
Not yet?
# 沒大 沒大
No, no, no
# 下次來
Next time
# 是呀 摘那麼(大)[SIC]多你也 你也拿不到是不是
Exactly! Don't take too much. You can't carry that much, right?
# 拿得到
Yes, I can!
# 拿不到 走走走走回去啦 大陽那麼大
No, you can't! Go, go go! Let's go back! The sun is so strong now.
# 你看 這青瓜
Look! The cucumber...
# 太浪費啦
What a waste!
# 這種青的很好吃的哦
These green ones are really tasty, you know.
# 額 這蕉還沒開花就長得那麼茂盛
Eh! The bananas, they're already growing so well, though there are still no flowers.
# 劉楚萱走啦 不要啦
Liu Chuxuan, let's go! We're not taking it.
# 你要是不是
You want it, don't you?
# 可以 給你
Alright. Take it!
# 媽媽
Mama!
# 今天晚上煮給你吃啊
I'll cook it for your dinner tonight, alright?
# 要不要吃
You want it?
# 要
Yes
# 要吃
You want.
# 哇 你看 摘了那麼多
Wa! Look! I've picked so many!
# 兄弟家的苦瓜在這裡哦
My buddy's bitter gourds are here.
# 下去看一下
Let me go down and have a look.
# 看有沒有
I'm gonna see if there are any,
# 哎呀 好多哇
Aya! A lot!
# 啊 在這乘一下涼
Ah! Let me take a shelter and cool down here.
# 好累啦
I'm exhausted.
# 爸爸 這裡有一個
Daddy! Here's one!
# 嗯 這個不要去動
Um! Make sure that you're not touching it.
# 這裡好多 好多苦瓜
Here are a lot, a lot of bitter gourds.
# 順便摘一點回去
Why don't we pick some back home?
# 苦瓜你也要哇
You want a bitter gourd too?
# 拿著
Hold it.
# 放在這裡
Put it here.
# 在這等一下我啊
Wait for me here.
# 這裡一個
Here's one.
# 你看 這樣的苦瓜
Look! This kind of bitter gourds,
# 我們本地的小苦瓜 很好吃的
are the local little bitter gourds here. They're really tasty.
# 香味十足
A rich scent of bitter gourd
# 這個也很靚的 這個
This one is also beautiful, this one.
# 今天晚上就可以釀苦瓜啦
Then tonight, we can have stuffed bitter gourd,
# 還有苦瓜炒肉
and also bitter gourd fried with pork,
# 還有紅燒苦瓜
and also stewed bitter gourd.
# 兄弟家吃不完 那麼多他哪裡吃的完
My buddy can't finish them. How can he finish them? There are so many.
# 我幫他吃一點
I'm here to help him.
# 別浪費啦
Don't waste the food.
# 哎喲
Ayo!
# 它這個棍子 放這裡踢腳
The rod is here, it's here to set me up.
# 把這個大的給你
This big one is for you.
# 這裡有一個是不是
Here's one, right?
# 那裡也有一個
There's another one!
# 夠啦 夠啦 夠啦 可以啦 別那麼貪心
Enough, enough, enough. It's alright now! Don't be so greedy!
# 那麼小就那麼貪心
You're still a baby and you're already so greedy.
# 拿都你都拿不到啦
You can't even take anymore!
# 走啦 我們回家家 走走
Let's go! Home sweet home! Let's go!
# 夠啦
It's enough.
# 不要那麼多
We don't need too many.
# 放到冰箱裡面凍一下
Let's chill it in the fridge.
# 吃一個再說
Let's share one first.
# 用這個水流沖一下 這個西瓜
I'm gonna rinse the watermelon, with the running water.
# 更快冷
It will cool down much faster.
# 這個 曬 曬燙了的西瓜吃會拉肚 會拉肚子的哦
This, a watermelon heated under the sun, is gonna give you a bad, stom..., a bad stomach.
# 刀都磿好啦
The knife is already sharpened.
# 就等著這個西瓜 冷了就吃
Let wait until the watermelon, cools down.
# 這個水龍頭 那麼慢它的速度
The tap is, why is it so slow?
# 流的 流水的速度太慢啦
The water, the water flows too slowly.
# 泡了一個小時
An hour has passed.
# 熟啦
It's ripe.
# 把這個
Let me...
# 哎呀 好紅
Aya! It's so red!
# 差點跑啦
It almost ran away.
# 哇 手 你手拿開
Wa! Hand! Get your hand off!
# 等一下 等一下
A moment, a moment!
# 等下啊
A moment, okay?
# 等下
A moment
# 我切一塊給你吃啊
I give you a piece, alright?
# 快點 你先去吃
C'mon! Take it first!
# 坐那旁邊吃啊
Sit over there and finish it, okay?
# 吃完來啊
Finish it, alright?
# 哇 這西瓜好紅啊
Wa! This watermelon is so red!
# 而且還有沙的哦
And it's grainy too.
# 兄弟肯定用有機肥種出來的 絕對好吃
My buddy must have grown it with organic fertiliser. It's absolutely tasty.
# 先嘗一下 看好不好吃
Let me have a try first, and see if it's tasty.
# 嗯
Um!
# 可以喲
Not bad!
# 不要來
Stand clear!
# 太甜啦 這個 (註︰這裡用"too"好像怎麼搞都是負面意思，改一下用字較好)
It's really really sweet, this,
# 這西瓜
this watermelon.
# 這瓜瓜太甜啦 是不是
The melon is really sweetie sweetie, isn't it?
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 吃相不好
My eating manner is bad.
My manner is bad.
# 不要把啦
Don't film me.